A Guide to the Hannah Allen Jeter Weiser papers, 1906-1983
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Hannah Allen Jeter Weiser papers, 1906-1983
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
1991/Jul/14
1.3 linear feet.
Weiser, Hannah Allen Jeter
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Nannie Anderson of Richmond, Virginia, June 1991.
Biographical Information
Hannah Allen Jeter Wesier (1897-1990) was born in Amelia County, Virginia. As as child she attended Clifton Forge Seminary, a girls boarding and day school located in Alleghany County. Later she studied nursing at St. Elizabeth's Hospital School for Nurses in Richmond, Virginia and graduated in 1931. She then attended the Richmond Division of the College of William & Mary (later named the Richmond Professional Institute) to study public health nursing and completed the program in 1936. She worked as a public health nurse in several places in Virginia during her career including Falls Church, Front Royal, and Richmond. She was a member of various nursing and public health associations including the American Nurses Association, American Public Health Association, Graduate Nurses Association of Virginia, and National Organization for Public Health Nursing.
Weiser married Raymond Ware Weiser of Clarendon, Virginia in the 1930s.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials related primarily to Wesier's education and career as a public health nurse and a few of her personal papers. These papers include course notes, some correspondence, drawings, medical pamphlets, maps, newspaper clippings, and a scrapbook.
Series 1: Educational and Professional papers, 1917-1978. These materials include her class notes from nursing school, materials from the Instructive Visiting Nurse Association, medical reprints, a collection of assorted medical pamphlets, and alumni materials from St. Elizabeth's Hospital School for Nurses and the Richmond Professional Institute School of Nursing, both of which Weiser attended.
Series 2: Personal papers, 1906-1983. This series includes correspondence, drawings and sketches, newspaper clippings, and a scrapbook which contains her Virginia State Board of Nurse Examiniers registration cards along with numerous membership cards for alumni and nursing organizations, letters, pictures, and other personal items.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into two series:
Series 1, Educational and Professional papers, 1917-1978.
Series 2, Personal papers, 1906-1983.
There was no discernable original arrangement for this material so like materials were grouped together. Files are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Contents List
- Educational and Professional papers 1917-1978 (Box 1)
  - Chart: Instructive, Nursing and Misc. Visits 1926-1935 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Instructive Visiting Nurse Association 1964, 1967 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Johns Hopkins Hospital Training School for Nurses, class notes 1930 or 1931 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Weiser took one or more courses at Johns Hopkins Hospital while a student at St. Elizabeth's.
  - Medical pamphlets (Box-folder 1:4)
    Pamphlets on a variet of medical topics including arthritis, cancer, flu, head lice, heart attacks, infant care, and STDs.
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Public health nursing, class notes and assignments 1935 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Reprints 1929-1935 (Box-folder 1:7)
    Reprints are primarily articles written by physicians at St. Elizabeth's Hospital.
  - Richmond Professional Institute School of Nursing, alumni letter no date, 1962 (Box-folder 1:8)
    Contains Season's Greeting messages from RPI and the first alumni letter from 1962.
  - St. Elizabeth's Hospital School for Nurses, class notes and assignments 1928-1930 (Box-folder 1:9-10)
  - St. Elizabeth's Hospital School for Nurses, monthly student reports 1928-1930 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - St. Elizabeth's Hospital School for Nurses, Scattered White Caps newsletter 1961, 1978 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - School notebook 1917 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Personal papers 1906-1983 (Box 1)
  - Artifacts (Box-folder 1:14)
    Includes a school ennant for Clifton Forge Seminary, a first aid instructor pin, and a Public Health Serivce name badge.
  - Correspondence 1922-1975 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Drawings and sketches (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Maps no date, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1:17)
    Includes maps of Fairfax County and a map of Virginia for 1938-1939.
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Programs 1934, 1966 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - St. Paul's Church, The Parish Register 1929 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Scrapbook and loose inserts (Box-folder 1:22-23)
  - University of Virginia materials 1922, 1935 (Box-folder 1:24)
    Includes a booklet on the school, a brochure for the Good Roads National Essay Contest sponsored by the school in 1922, and the Fairfax County Geography Supplement complied and published by UVA and the Fairfax County School Board, 1925.